---
title: "Chapter 1: Leverage – How Small Players Can Move the World"
author: "Dr. Cheung Chi Hung (Samson)"
date: "2026-04-08"
doi: "PENDING"
categories:
  - Management
  - Strategic Management
tags:
  - leverage
  - game theory
  - institutional economics
  - 80-20 rule
  - Singapore
  - GBA
  - Northern Metropolis
  - 15th Five-Year Plan
abstract: |
  This chapter introduces the strategic concept of leverage through a case study of Singapore’s transformation and a personal reflection on traditional Chinese martial arts philosophy. Drawing on game theory (Schelling, 1960), institutional economics (North, 1990), and the 80/20 principle (Pareto, 1906), it develops a three‑level framework for small players to gain competitive advantage. The analysis integrates the 2026 PwC Global CEO Survey (N=4,454), UNCTAD maritime trade data, and the latest developments in China’s low‑altitude economy and Hong Kong’s Northern Metropolis. The framework is then extended to the Greater Bay Area and aligned with the national 15th Five‑Year Plan. The chapter concludes that for resource‑constrained actors, victory lies not in matching incumbent scale, but in superior strategic positioning.
---

## 1. A Question That Reshaped My Thinking

In 2012, while pursuing my MBA at the City University of Macau, I met Dr. Ip Yan‑kit. He asked a deceptively simple question: **“Why can a small company defeat a much larger competitor?”**

I had no answer.

He smiled and explained: “A small company does not need to compete on size. It simply needs to identify a **lever** – a point from which it can move the world.”

This question became the foundation for my subsequent inquiry into strategic management. Decades earlier, my father had spoken of our family’s martial arts heritage – the Zhang family’s short‑range boxing (張氏短拳), which emphasised “using the opponent’s force, finding the weak point, and striking with precision.” The parallel between the boxer’s leverage and the strategist’s lever became immediately apparent.

---

## 2. Theoretical Foundations of Leverage

### 2.1 Game Theory and Bargaining Power

In *The Strategy of Conflict*, Schelling (1960) argued that bargaining power derives from the ability to present an **irreplaceable alternative**. Dixit and Nalebuff (2023) extended this to **commitment strategies** – making threats or promises credible. For a small state, this means locking large players into dependence on a unique resource or service.

### 2.2 Institutional Economics and “Order Rent”

North (1990) showed that stable institutions reduce transaction costs and create lasting competitive advantage. Rodrik (2024) demonstrated that high‑quality legal systems generate **“order rent”** – the premium that market participants willingly pay for predictability and efficiency. Jiang (2025) highlighted how small open economies rapidly adapt their institutions to global changes.

### 2.3 The 80/20 Principle

Pareto (1906) observed that 80% of outcomes often come from 20% of inputs. Koch (2023) updated this for the digital age, showing that focusing on critical nodes multiplies returns. UNCTAD (2025) confirms that 80% of global maritime trade flows through just 20% of key straits.

---

## 3. Singapore: A Paradigm of Strategic Leverage

Despite having no natural resources, Singapore’s GDP per capita now exceeds that of the United States (World Bank, 2025). Its success lies in **three interconnected layers**:

**3.1 Geographic Fulcrum** 
Singapore sits at the Strait of Malacca, through which 25% of global oil and 30% of container traffic passes (UNCTAD, 2025).

**3.2 Institutional Strength** 
It built a one‑stop service ecosystem – bunkering, insurance, finance, legal arbitration – within a transparent, efficient legal framework, creating **order rent** (North, 1990; Rodrik, 2024).

**3.3 Technological Enhancement** 
Singapore invested heavily in AI‑driven port logistics, transforming itself into a **technological node** – exactly the framework proposed by Eisenhardt and Brown (2024) in *Harvard Business Review*.

---

## 4. Contemporary Data: Why Small Players Have an Opening

The 2026 PwC Global CEO Survey (N=4,454) reveals that **nearly 40% of CEOs believe their organisations will not survive the coming decade** if they maintain current trajectories. At the same time, early AI adopters are pulling away – companies with embedded AI achieve profit margins roughly **4 percentage points higher** than peers (McKinsey, 2026).

The low‑altitude economy in China is another example. Industry estimates place its 2025 market size at **RMB 1.5 trillion**, and 2026 is expected to be the first year of normalised operations. Over **17,000** related enterprises now exist nationwide, with Guangdong province alone hosting **15,000** (30% of the national total) and producing **6.9 million** civilian drones in 2025.

For small players, the window to capture value is narrowing, but decisive action can leapfrog incumbents. The World Economic Forum (2026) notes that the AI era will favour agility over scale – exactly where small states and firms can excel.

---

## 5. A Three‑Level Framework for Strategic Leverage

| Level | Action | Theoretical Support |
|-------|--------|---------------------|
| **1. Find your fulcrum** | Identify the 20% of nodes that drive 80% of outcomes | Pareto (1906); Koch (2023) |
| **2. Build institutional strength** | Reduce transaction costs, create order rent, become irreplaceable | North (1990); Rodrik (2024) |
| **3. Embrace technology** | Turn geographic or resource advantages into technological advantages | Eisenhardt & Brown (2024); Teece (2023) |

This framework aligns with Teece’s (2023) **dynamic capabilities** theory – sensing, seizing, and transforming to maintain advantage. It also echoes the Zhang family’s short‑boxing philosophy: *“Use the opponent’s force, find the weak point, and strike with precision”* – the very essence of leverage.

---

## 6. Implications for Hong Kong, the GBA, and National Strategy

### 6.1 Hong Kong’s Northern Metropolis
The Northern Metropolis – now one‑third of Hong Kong’s land – is the territory’s new economic engine. The **15th Five‑Year Plan (2026–2030)** explicitly mandates its accelerated development. The Hong Kong government has allocated **HK$150 billion** from the Exchange Fund for Northern Metropolis infrastructure – the first such transfer since 1984. By positioning it as an innovation hub, Hong Kong can create its own “fulcrum”.

### 6.2 The Greater Bay Area (GBA)
The GBA now exceeds RMB 15 trillion in output and is driven by the “Shenzhen‑Hong Kong‑Guangzhou” innovation cluster – ranked first globally in the Global Innovation Index (WIPO, 2025). The Hetao Hong Kong Park, opened in late 2025, provides a testing ground for cross‑border policies.

### 6.3 National Strategy
The 15th Five‑Year Plan emphasises high‑quality development, new quality productive forces, and technological self‑reliance. Hong Kong’s role as a “super connector” and “super value‑adder” within the dual circulation framework is exactly the kind of institutional advantage that creates order rent at the regional level.

---

## 7. Conclusion

From the ancient philosophy of Zhang family boxing to Singapore’s national strategy, the principle remains constant: **small players achieve victory not through superior size, but through superior strategic positioning.**

The three‑level framework – find your fulcrum, build institutional strength, embrace technology – offers a practical path for individuals, firms, and regions to turn constraints into advantages. As the PwC data shows, the window to act is narrowing; but for those who act decisively, the opportunity to move the world has never been greater.

---

## References

1. Dixit, A.K., & Nalebuff, B.J. (2023). *The Art of Strategy*. W.W. Norton.
2. Eisenhardt, K.M., & Brown, S.L. (2024). Strategic leverage in the age of AI. *Harvard Business Review*, 102(3), 78–87.
3. Jiang, J. (2025). Institutional adaptation in small open economies. *Journal of Institutional Economics*, 21(2), 215–234.
4. Koch, R. (2023). *The 80/20 Principle* (6th ed.). Nicholas Brealey.
5. McKinsey Global Institute. (2026). *The next 10 years: Resilience and reinvention*.
6. North, D.C. (1990). *Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance*. Cambridge University Press.
7. Pareto, V. (1906). *Manual of Political Economy*.
8. PwC. (2026). *29th Annual Global CEO Survey*.
9. Rodrik, D. (2024). Institutions and economic growth. *Journal of Economic Perspectives*, 38(3), 145–168.
10. Schelling, T.C. (1960). *The Strategy of Conflict*. Harvard University Press.
11. Teece, D.J. (2023). Dynamic capabilities and strategic management. *Strategic Management Journal*, 44(5), 1123–1145.
12. UNCTAD. (2025). *Review of Maritime Transport 2025*.
13. World Bank. (2025). *World Development Indicators 2025*.
14. World Economic Forum. (2026). *The Future of Jobs Report 2026*.
15. World Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO). (2025). *Global Innovation Index 2025*.

---